Alvin G. Thomas Curriculum vitae

# CONTACT Information

Johns Hopkins University E-mail: alvin@jhmi.edu
School of Medicine, Department of Surgery Github: alvinthomas
720 Rutland Ave, Turner 34 Twitter: @alvinthomas13
Baltimore, MD 21205 USA LinkedIn: @alvinthomas13

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

Utilizing Epidemiologic Methods in Transplantion: My research explores interesting epidemiologic questions across the field of solid organ transplantation with focus areas in living kidney donor health and liver transplantation outcomes. I am also involved in the development of a number of eHealth tools designed to connect, educate, and empower transplant donors and recipients.

# CURRENT POSITION

Research Data Analyst, Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine, Department of Surgery Epidemiology Research Group in Transplantation August 2016 to present

#### EDUCATION

### Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health, Baltimore, MD

MSPH, International Health, May 2016

- Focus: Global Disease Epidemiology and Control (GDEC)
- Thesis Topic: The mLAKE Community Trial: Using mHealth to Empower CHWs to Encourage Combination HIV Prevention
- Adviser: Larry W. Chang, MD, MPH

#### Washington and Lee University, Lexington, VA

BS, Chemistry-Engineering, May 2014

- *Honors* in Engineering
- Thesis: Plasticity in Dissociated Neuronal Networks under Chronic Stimulation
- Adviser: Jonathan Erickson, PhD
- Minor in Poverty and Human Capabilities

# REFEREED JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Thomas AG**, Henderson ML, Shaffer A, Massie AB, Luo X, Holscher CM, Purnell TS, Lentine K, Segev DL. The National Landscape of Living Kidney Donor Follow-up in the United States. *American Journal of Transplantation*. In Press.
- [2] Long A, Mbabali I, Hutton HE, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Mulamba J, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Gray RH, Wawer MJ, Nakigozi G, Chang LW. Design and Implementation of a Community Health Worker HIV Treatment and Prevention Intervention in an HIV Hotspot Fishing Community in Rakai, Uganda. *Journal* of the International Association of Providers of AIDS Care. In Press.
- [3] Perin J, Thomas AG, Oldja L, Ahmed S, Parvin T, Bhuyian SI, Sarker B, Biswas SK, Faruque AS, Sack RB, and George CM, 2016. Geophagy is associated with growth faltering in children in rural Bangladesh. *The Journal of Pediatrics*. 2016 Nov 30; 178:34-9. doi:10.1016/j.jpeds.2016.06.077

# Conference Talks

[1] Henderson M, **Thomas AG**, Massie A, Luo X, Shaffer A, Holscher C, Segev DL. The Unfunded OPTN/UNOS Mandate of Living Kidney Donor Follow-up: Fewer than 50% of Centers in Compliance. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 - May 3, 2017. Presentor: Henderson M

### Conference Posters

- [1] **Thomas AG**, Shaffer A, Massie A, Segev DL. Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 May 3, 2017.
- [2] Thomas AG, Massie A, Garonzik-Wang J, Lentine K, Henderson M, Segev DL. Landscape of Multiple Donations from a Living Donor in the US. In: American Transplant Congress, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 - May 3, 2017.
- [3] Shrestha P, Rasmussen S, **Thomas AG**, Ferguson S, Massie A, Segev DL. Access to Living Donor Kidney Transplantation in Nepal. In: *American Transplant Congress*, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 May 3, 2017.
- [4] Halpern S, Thomas AG, Holscher C, Massie A, Henderson M, Anjum S, Locke J, Segev DL. Sexual Dysfunction Among Living Kidney Donors. In: American Transplant Congress, Chicago, IL, USA, April 29 - May 3, 2017.
- [5] Bannon J, Wickliffe C, Thomas AG, Klingbell A, Hiller J, Halpern S, Segev DL, Henderson M. An Interdisciplinary Task Force to Engage Living Kidney Donors and Improve Follow-up Compliance. In: UNOS Transplant Management Forum, Orlando, FL, USA, April 25-27, 2017.
- [6] Thomas AG, Henderson ML, Massie AB, Shaffer A, Luo X, Holscher CM, Segev DL. Fewer than 50% of Transplant Centers Fully Comply with OPTN Living Donor Follow-up Policy. In: American Society of Transplant Surgeons, Miami, FL, USA, January 26-29, 2017.
- [7] Hapern SE, Thomas AG, Holscher CM, Massie AB, Henderson ML, Anjum S, Locke JE, Segev DL. Sexual Dysfunction Among Living Kidney Donors. In: American Society of Transplant Surgeons, Miami, FL, USA, January 26-29, 2017.
- [8] Long A, Hutton H, Mbabali I, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Mulamba J, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Gray R, Wawer M, Nakigozi G, Chang LW. Evaluation of a Motivational Interviewing-Informed, mHealth-Supported CHW Training Program to Promote HIV Treatment and Prevention in a HIV Hotspot Ugandan Fishing Community. In: International Association of Providers of AIDS Care, Fort Lauderdale, FL, USA, May 9-11, 2016.
- [9] Chang LW, Mbabali I, Kong X, Hutton H, Long A, Thomas AG, Bugos E, Ssekasanvu J, Kennedy C, Amico KR, Nalugoda F, Reynolds SJ, Quinn T, Serwadda D, Gray R, Wawer M, Nakigozi G. A Cluster-Randomized Trial to Promote Combination HIV Prevention Using mHealth-Supported CHWs in a High-Prevalence Ugandan Fishing Community: Design and Baseline Characteristics of the mLAKE Trial. In: International AIDS Conference, Durban, South Africa, July 18-22, 2016.
- [10] Thomas AG, Erickson J, Strickland K, Barnes A. Iterative Gaussian mixture model splitting of multimodal PSTH for studying activity dependent changes in cultured network connectivity. In: Society for Neuroscience, San Deigo, CA, USA, November 9-13, 2013.

# RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

#### Research Assistant | Rakai Health Science Program | 2015-2016

Engaged in two mHealth implementation science research projects aimed at improving uptake of HIV services in rural Uganda. Developed data analysis code in R for monitoring and evaluation activities. Trained community health workers and study staff. Assisted in the development and testing of two mHealth applications. Contributed to study questionnaires, standard operating protocols, and training materials.

#### Data Manager | Johns Hopkins University | 2016

 Performed data management activities to ensure data quality using SAS, EpiInfo, and Stata for the NSEBA Study which aims to improve detection of pediatric HIV in Zambia.

#### Research Assistant | International Vaccine Access Center | 2014-2015

 Performed data abstraction for a systematic review to determine the global burden of Haemophilus influenza type B, Streptococcus Pneumoniae, and Neisseria meningitides.

# Student Reseracher | Shepherd Poverty Program | 2013

Analyzed data from the CDC Health, 2011 report to present longitudinal data analysis on the relationship between socioeconomic status and health status. Funded by the University Research Scholarship. Advisor: Harlan Beckley, PhD

#### Biomedical Engineering Technician | Engineering World Health | 2013

• Fully repaired 20 medical devices, took full inventories of the Rubavu hospital and its ten surrounding health clinics, and conceptualized a novel medical device to perform lab equipment calibrations in resource-scarce environments.

#### AMERICORPS SERVICE

# Robotics Program Founder | Lexington City Schools | 2011-2014

 Created and ran a program that uses Lego NXT robots to introduce middle school and elementary students to robotics, computer science, and engineering design utilizing a \$2500 grant from NSF.

# Shift Leader | Campus Kitchens Project | 2011-2014

 Addressed local hunger as a ServSafe-certified manager by supervising shifts that collected, prepared, and served over 300 meals/week.

#### Trip Coordinator | Volunteer Venture Program | 2011-2013

• Coordinated three weeklong service trips for incoming students, which involves budget management and logistical planning.

# Therapeutic Nursery Intern | Kennedy Krieger Institute | 2011

• Conducted play-therapy sessions with homeless toddlers and their families. Provided care for the children and assisted with an active study in child psychology.

#### Patient Eligibility Intern | Rockbridge Area Health Center | 2010-2012

• Helped manage the medical database, helped eligible patients acquire free medication from pharmaceutical companies, and answered patient questions by phone.

# SOFTWARE SKILLS

# Statistical/Numerical Analysis:

• R, Stata, SAS, MATLAB, Maple

# Computer Programming:

• C, C++, Java, Python, SQL

#### Version Control:

• Git, SVN

# Productivity and Editing Software:

- Atom, Xcode, RStudio
- $T_EX$  (LATEX, BIBTEX)
- Microsoft Office, LibreOffice, Google Docs, iWork, EndNote
- GIMP, Adobe Photoshop

#### Operating Systems:

• Apple OS X, Microsoft Windows, Linux (Fedora)

#### AWARDS

# American Transplant Congress 2017

- Best of Congress Poster for "Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure"
- Poster of Distiction for "Use of Pulsatile Perfusion Modifies the Effect of Delayed Graft Function on Graft Failure"

#### Johns Hopkins University Bloomberg School of Public Health

• Center for Global Health Established Field Placement/Pilot Grant, 2015

#### Washington and Lee University

- Algernon Sydney Sullivan Award, 2014
- Omicron Delta Kappa Leader of the Year, 2014
- Sigma Pi Sigma Physics Honor Society, 2013
- Johnson Opportunity Grant, 2013
- Evans International Grant, 2013
- Avis P. Waring Scholarship, 2013
- Omicron Delta Kappa Leadership Honor Society, 2013
- Beta Beta Beta Biological Honor Society, 2011
- Bonner Scholarship, 2010
- Johnson Scholarship, 2010-2014